hey what's up guys my name is Aero and
welcome back to my C++ Series so you're
using Linux to develop C++ code okay
cool let's cover how we can set up the
tools we need on Linux so that we can
make C++ programs now of course there
are so many different tools out there so
many different ways to write and build
your code I'm going to cover one of
those ways one that I personally like I
hope you're ready to do some serious
setting up I mean you've chosen Linux so
obviously you're going to be prepared to
do some work basically we're going to
use cmake to generate project files for
an IDE called code light code light is a
nice lightweight IDE that basically does
pretty much everything you would expect
but isn't too heavyweight and just lets
us write our code in a nice way so let's
go ahead and set everything up so we've
got a virtual box VM here running mint
18.1 and I'm using KDE as my GUI so if I
go ahead and open a terminal we can get
started so the first thing I like to do
is set up a directory here called Dev
which is basically going to hold all of
our development stuff um we'll make a
and then basically inside here we'll
have a like a folder for each project so
I'll make a directory called Hello World
um which is going to be uh what we're
going to do here now we're going to set
up a basic H World project now in terms
of the applications that we actually
have to install we basically need the
ones that we really need are a compiler
cake and code light so the first thing
you're going to want to do to install
all that is do pseudo app to get update
that's just going to basically update
and type in your root password that's
going to basically update all of our
package packages our package
repositories and then once that's done
we can actually install the packages we
need so what we need are uh we'll do
aptg install I like to use Vim as my
terminal text editor um and then we'll
get g++ as our compiler we'll get code
light as our IDE and we will get uh cake
and then just hit enter you can see
It'll take 198 megabytes Y and this will
take a while okay so once that is done
let's go ahead and clear this so we've
got nothing in our directory right now I
like to make a directory called source
and that's where I'll actually put all
of my source files I'm going to just
create a file in the source directory
called main.cpp I'm just not I'm not
going to write anything into it I'm just
going to create the empty file um and
we'll actually let code light handle
that file for us we're going to need to
set up a cmake file and then I also like
to set up a build script so that we've
got an easy way to generate a project so
in terms of cmake we'll make that first
I'm just going to use Vim you can use
any text editor you like the file is
going to be called cmak lists. text and
this is going to basically just instruct
cmake how we want to actually generate
our code light project file so first of
all we'll specify a minimum version of
cake that we need um as a good rule of
thumb I like to just roll with version
3.5 we'll then give our project a name
so I'll call this hollow
world and then we'll set up some
variables essentially so uh in terms of
like flags that we want to use for
compilation um we want to use the
existing ones so that's uh basically the
existing cmake cxx Flags which are the
compilation Flags um but in terms of
what we actually want to do we want to
add we want to display all warnings um
errors of course and then in terms of
like which standard Library we use um
you can use C++ 11 C+ 14 doesn't really
doesn't really matter for this project
since we'll be just using we'll be
printing hello world but um we can roll
with 14 just to Future proof ourselves a
little bit um we'll create a variable
here called Source directory um and I'll
actually set this to be uh the project
Source
directory um and
then essentially just a folder called
source so the project Source directory
is the directory we're currently in and
then inside there I'm just making I've
just made a directory called source and
that's where all my source files are so
that works out pretty well um so we've
set up these variables right those two
lines were just variable we've set our
flags and we've set our source directory
now we actually need to somehow tell the
compiler which files to compile so um
again using cmake we can just use a
globe for that so basically I'm going to
specify that my source files are going
to be in that Source directory and that
Source directory is just this variable
that I've made up here right and then
basically anything inside that directory
that ends in C++ and CPP I want to
compile now if you had include
directories and stuff you would also
want to set that up but for now we're
not going to do that that um we'll just
add executable so this is going to be
our Target um hello world is our project
name and then which files we want to
pass into there are going to be our
source files if you had again an include
directory or something you would also
pass it in here but there we go that's
all of our stuff uh that's that's our
entire cake lists done so let's write
and quit now we'll set up a script that
will run seake for us so I'll call this
build.sh now this isn't really going to
build our code it's just going to
generate the project and I'll show you
kind of how this works in a minute but
basically the first thing we want to do
is make sure that bash is going to be
able to execute it and all that so we'll
add uh Bin sh as every bash script will
have um then we'll do cmake uh- G so in
terms of the target we're going to be
using Code light Unix make files you can
also use something like ninja if you
like probably a bit better than this but
this is just a bit easier to set up um
and then as far as my build type goes
I'm actually going to set that to debug
my see make build type um because
generating a debug configuration is
probably what we want anyway since we'll
be debugging a lot and you want to make
sure the code light has a capital l here
um and that's it we can write and quit
that and that's how it's going to be our
entire script very very simple so now
we're ready to run our script now in
order to run a script in Linux you have
to mark it as as executable so we'll
just do CH mod plus X and then build our
s so we're just adding the executable
flag to the build.sh file now we can run
it and hopefully if you did everything
correctly you can see that it's written
some build files for us so if we look at
the directory you'll see there's a
number of new files here um the ones
that we kind of care about are hell
world. project and Hell world. workpace
there are make files as well but um you
can see that those kind of the important
ones so now how do we open this in code
light well I like to just open it
through the terminal so you can just
type in code light and then hello world.
workpace now if you want to open it in
the background so that you can still use
your terminal just add an ampersand onto
the end hit enter and code light should
open now you're probably going to want
to run through this setup I don't really
care so I'm going to hit cancel um as
you can see we've got our project here
and our
Target just make this a bit bigger um
we've got our include directories so
this is where all of our includes go
sources just going to go in here um
we'll double click the file to open it
I'm going to just basically type out a
simple Hollow World application so we'll
say
and we'll do our little cn. getet as
well all right save that if you want to
build it you can just hit build and
build
project output's down here and you can
see that everything's fine zero errors
zero warnings we're ready to go if we go
back to
terminal and I do an LS you can see
we've got a hollow world uh file and
it's actually
executable right so that's our actual
program so let's go ahead and run that
there you go hello world we've written
our first application if you want to run
it inside here one thing I like to do is
just go to preferences and make it use
the built-in terminal emulator and then
you can just do build run we can build
it and execute it and you can see here
it is running inside of code light all
right that's it Linux is set up we're
ready to write some code we're ready to
learn some C Plus+ over the next few
videos we're going to cover how C++
actually works because that's the key to
learning how to write C++ properly until
then you can follow me on Twitter and
Instagram and if you really like this
series you can support my videos by
pledging on patreon.com for/ Theo until
next time goodbye vom